"Foods to Help Protect Your
Arteries from Saturated Fat"
If you compare the artery function
of those who don't eat meat
to those who do, the healthy
ability of arteries to dilate and
let more blood flow is significantly
better among those eating vegetarian.
And not just by a little.
We're talking four times better.
Well, duh, vegetarians tend to be
younger, smoke less, be slimmer,
and have lower rates of diabetes,
high cholesterol, high blood pressure,
and heart disease. But the
researchers controlled for all that.
They only let healthy
nonsmokers into the study,
and recruited a group of meat eaters
who were just about as slim,
on average, and had about
the same blood pressures,
even practically the
same cholesterol---
a really healthy cohort
of omnivores---
yet they still got their arteries
handed to them by the vegetarians.
And the longer someone
was meat-free, the better.
The degree of superior artery
function correlated
with the number of years
eating meat-free.
Instead of their artery function
worsening over time as they aged,
it got better the longer
they ate that way.
This suggests that vegetarian
diets, by themselves,
have a direct beneficial effect
on artery function and may help
to account for the lower incidence
of atherosclerosis and
cardiovascular mortality.
Since researchers were able to
control for other known risk factors,
they figured it must be the food.
But what aspect of the food?
Is it simply the lack of the
deleterious effect of meat?
Or could it also be because the
vegetarians may simply be eating
more whole healthy
plant foods, for example,
up to a serving a day
more vegetables.
When researchers compared two crappy
meals, Sausage and Egg McMuffins
to Frosted Flakes, and found the
fatty meal impaired artery function
within hours but the sugary meal
didn't, they blamed the fat.
But it may just be the animal fat,
since high-fat whole plant foods
like nuts don't have the same effect.
In fact, if you look at
a systematic review
of all the randomized
controlled trials on the effect
of nut consumption
on artery function,
you find that nuts actually
make things better over time.
Enough to counter the artery-crippling
effects of a salami sandwich?
Let's find out. And the answer is
yes for walnuts, but no for almonds.
Just like there are some fruits
that are better than others,
like blueberries over bananas,
there are some nuts that are better
than others, and walnuts appear
to be the blueberries of nuts.
What about the blueberry of
berries: blueberries themselves?
A randomized, controlled crossover
trial of cooked blueberries,
raw blueberries, or
no blueberries at all.
If you feed people buns made out
of white flour, eggs, butter, and salt,
and fill them mostly
full of sugar and eggs,
you get a gradual drop in artery
function over the next six hours.
But add the equivalent of a cup of
wild blueberries to that same bun,
and instead you get a big
boost in artery function,
almost as if you had just mixed
the blueberries with water.
About the same amount of strawberries
failed to rescue artery function
from the likes of two cheese blintzes
with whipped cream, a sugary syrup,
egg and bacon, but that is
quite a heavy load to bear.
What about acai berries versus a
meal with a similar amount of fat?
One and a half-frozen smoothie packs
with half a small banana in water
were able to significantly
rehabilitate arterial function
compared to a control smoothie
with the same banana and water
colored to look like the acai one,
though obviously it would
have tasted differently.
This group of researchers went
all out, though, and performed
a double-blind randomized
controlled trial with raspberries,
measuring artery function after
2 hours and then 24 hours after
drinking about 3/4 of a cup of frozen
red raspberries blended with water,
or about a cup and a half,
versus a placebo drink meant
to match both color and taste.
The fake berry drink had no effect on
artery function, but the other two did.
Note the 3/4 cup dose
seemed to work just as well
as the cup and a half dose, which
is what you see with blueberries:
the benefits plateau
after about a cup.
The bottom line is that consumption
of dietarily achievable amounts of
red raspberries acutely improves
artery function for up to 24 hours.
You say, "Yeah, but by the end of the
day you're only up like one percent."
Ah, but at a population level, each
one percent increase is associated
with a 12% reduction in risk
of a cardiovascular event
like a heart attack or stroke, all
from just having a berry smoothie.
What about berry juice?
Five different concentrations
of cranberry juice were used,
along with a placebo control evidently
indistinguishable in color and taste.
The 25% cranberry juice drink
gave a little bump at two hours;
the 50% juice was still
working eight hours later.
The 75% juice, the one that was nearly
pure juice, and the ultra-concentrated
juice also improved artery function
within hours of consumption.
But this, like that last raspberry
study, just involved straight berries
without some artery-crushing meal.
Would berry juice be able
to stop artery dysfunction
caused by a high-fat
meal this unhealthy,
squeezing down artery
function within hours?
Researchers created a cocktail
of grapes, lingonberry, blueberry,
strawberry, and black aronia berry
and were able to turn this
into this. No significant change
after the high-fat meal.
Of course, if you had just
drunk those berries alone,
you'd probably get an improvement,
but it's better than nothing.
Well, what about something a little
less exotic than black aronia berries.
What about OJ?
Participants were provided a high-fat
meal of ham and cheese croissants,
along with either a cup of water,
orange juice, green tea, or red wine.
The arteries didn't much like the
croissants, and OJ was useless,
as was the green tea and red wine.
So it's probably best to not eat
ham and cheese croissants
in the first place.
In fact, drinking orange juice
with a fatty meal
could actually make things worse.
If you give people bacon and cheese
muffins with or without orange juice,
the OJ can lead to a prolongation
of elevated fat in the blood
as your body preferentially burns
for energy all the rapidly absorbed
free sugars in the juice, meaning
sugars not encased in cells walls,
as in those in whole fruit.